CAREER PROFILE

Experienced software engineer interested in architecting server-side applications. Strong knowledge on Java, Spring, JavaScript & TypeScript based applications. Worked on both product & services industry with over 9 years of experience.

SKILLS & PROFICIENCY (exp. in years)

Java tools

Spring(6), Spring boot(6), Spring cloud(2), Apache commons(6), Tomcat(10)

JavaScript tools

Nodejs(2), TypeScript(2), Expressjs(2), Passportjs(2)

DB

PostgreSQL(6), MySQL(2), Firebase(2), Cassandra(1)

UI tools

Vaadin(4), jQuery(1)

Web

HTML, CSS

Identity Management

OAuth2.0(3), Openid(3), UAA(3)

Cloud platform

GCP(3), Cloud Functions(3), GKE, AWS

Build tools

Maven(6), Jenkins(1), Gradle(1)

Testing

JMeter(2), JUnit(3), Mockito(1), TDD(6)

Version control

Git(4), Github(4), Gitlab(2), SVN(2), Mercurial(1)

IDE

VSCode(2), Eclipse(6)

EXPERIENCES

9 years

2019 - Present

SaaS Technology Consultant

Metal Street - B2B marketplace for steel trading

Architected sales module in firebase with multitenant db & cloud functions. Design was based on CORS, DDD principles.

Implemented user authentication using Openid & OAuth2 token introspection endpoints.

Integration with zoho books for handling sales module.

Implementation of integration middleware using cloud functions serverless technology.

Technology summary

Nodejs, TypeScript, Firebase-NoSQL, Google cloud functions, OAuth2

SaaS Technology Consultant

2017 - 2018

Mediapp - B2B app for pharma stockists, chemists & distributors

Architected integration middleware as event-driven for sales module in google cloud functions. Handling sales module using zoho books api.

App notification for sales module using Firebase Cloud Messaging.

Designed & implemented batch processing jobs in cloud functions. For handling long running jobs, tasks are split into small units which executes in cloud functions.

Handled 10k active users in cloud functions.

Handling of customer support.

Mentoring junior developers.

Binoy Varghese

Technical Architect

binoyhex@gmail.com

J +91 7483757462

in binoy-varghese

Resume

EDUCATION

B.Tech in Computer Science & Engineering

College of Engineering, Chengannur 2005 - 2009

LANGUAGES

English (Professional)

Hindi (Professional)

Malayalam (Native)

INTERESTS

Reading

Swimming

Gaming

· Nodejs, TypeScript, Firebase-NoSQL, Google cloud functions, Firebase cloud messaging

SaaS Technology Consultant

2017 - Present

Integration startup

Development of multitenant identity server.

Technology summary

· Java, Spring, Spring security, UAA, Openid, PostgreSQL

Technical Architect 2013 - 2017

Leanswift

Technical architect & leading development of eLink which is middleware for Infor M3 ERP. eLink provides integration between eCommerce, web, mobile applications and Infor M3 with secure access control.

Development of eLink using Spring Framework following TDD with documentation.

Implementation of authentication & access control using Spring Security.

Developed eLink Transaction manager using Spring Transaction Management.

Developed eLink Connection pooling using Apache commons pool.

Mentoring & leading of the development team.

Payment integration with pos device via JavaScript API.

Vaadin based apps for comactivity & Infor M3.

eLink support for Leanswift M3 apps marketplace.

Build automation using Jenkins.

Helped in recruitment, interview and mentoring for various teams in Leanswift.

Technology summary

· Java, Spring, Spring security, Openid, PostgreSQL, H2, Jenkins, Vaadin

Member of Technical Staff

2011 - 2013

Zoho - Team member of ManageEngine Netflow analyser

Implementing security to prevent csrf attacks using inhouse security framework.

Bug fixes and performance improvements.

Helped in testing netflow analyser for various use cases.

Helped in migrating Mysql db to PostgreSQL.

Helped in adding performance tuning of netflow analyser. Dynamically increasing java heap memory based on usage.

Technology summary

· Java, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, MySQL, PostgreSQL

Software Engineer 2010 - 2010

CCS Technologies

Developemnt of Exam management software.

Worked on both JavaScript & java.

Implemented ajax, jquery based frontend which communicates with tomcat server.

Technology summary

· Java, JavaScript, jQuery, HTML, CSS, MySQL

Trainee Engineer 2009 - 2010

Techieindex Solutions

Support engineer for debugging and bug fixing of inhouse framework.

Development of data grabber using Rome api - Java framework for RSS and Atom feeds.

Technology summary

· Java, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, MySQL